# Utkarsh Ranjan

La Jolla, CA 92037

📞 +1-914-267-5306 | 🔀 uranjan@ucsd.edu | 🖸 uranjan | 📠 linkedin.com/in/utkarsh | 🏔 ranjanutkarsh.github.io

#### PERSONAL PROFILE

Graduate student at The University of California San Diego pursuing my masters at the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering specializing in Machine Learning and Data Science (MLDS). Zealous about software engineering with 3 years of experience specializing in machine learning, python development, data analytics. Primarily, looking for SDE, Machine Learning/Data Engineer/Python Developer roles.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of California - San Diego, California | US

Sep 2022 – June 2024

 $M.S.\ in\ Electrical \& Computer\ Engineering.\ (Major.\ Machine\ Learning\ and\ Data\ Science)$ 

Relevant Courses: GPU Programming

Indian Institute of Technology (Banaras Hindu University), Varanasi | IN

Jul 2015 – May 2019

B. Tech. in Electrical Engineering

Relevant Courses: Parallel Computing, Distributed Computing, High Performance Computing

**SKILLS** 

Languages: Python, R, SQL, Java, C++, Matlab, C#, CUDA

Framework: Spark NLP, TensorFlow, Keras, OpenCV, sci-kit-learn, Flask, Elastic Search, Splunk, Kubernetes

Cloud Platform: Microsoft Azure, Google Cloud Platform, AWS

Database: Microsoft SQL, Hadoop, AWS, Mongo DB

Technologies/Dev Tools: JIRA, Tableau, Git, Power BI, Confluence, Github

**EXPERIENCE** 

Gartner,Inc Jun 2019 – Jun 2022

Data Science Associate | Services - Data Science Team

Gurgaon, IN

IRIS: Recommendation System | PySpark, AWS, SparkNLP, Scikit-learn, Pandas, Neo4j, Git

- Developed a Python based recommendation system to suggest actions for clients based on their digital footprints across 5 parameters.
- Created graph embedding with 12000+ client nodes using Neo4j to train models using activity history of peer connections

## $\textbf{GPR-IVR Survey: Comment Classification} \mid Spark NLP, Scikit-learn, Pandas$

- Developed a text classifier to mine the root causes of dissatisfaction from client feedback. Reached an F1- Score of 75% for determining action areas for corresponding business units
- Brought down the time spent from 2 weeks to 15 minutes for classifying client comments by creating a classification model using BERT
- Deployed trained scikit-learn ML models for spam classifier, entity recognition use-cases over PySpark real time ML pipeline using Natural Language Processing models.

#### SIVR: Creating a parameter to score client's engagement | Pandas, MongoDB

- Created a performance metric: SIVR using multivariate analysis over 20K client engagement data across 5 business units to calculate the quality of value interaction with clients
- Spearheaded the development of an automated mailing system for service executives to ensure swift issue resolution and tracking by bringing down turn around time from 90 mins to 15 mins.

Gartner,Inc
Summer Intern | Services - Data Science Team
May 2018 – Jul 2018
Gurgaon, IN

- Trained and test various supervised algorithms like Random Forest, Naïve Bayes and SVM using TF- IDF feature vectors to create a new FILTER in the tool achieved a classification accuracy of 83%
- Brought down the time spent from 15 hours per week to 2 hours by automating the process of report generation using python for efficient client service

### **Indian Institute of Space Science and Technology**

May 2017 – Jul 2017

 $Summer\ Intern\ |\ Department\ of\ Mathematics$ 

Trivandrum, IN

- Proposed a framework to capture the meaning of an unknown word by leveraging its root word and suffix through word embedding.
- Implemented Markov Chain Monte Carlo on UC Irvine Machine Learning Repository to achieve a macro- average precision of 91% over 11 classes.

## **ACHIEVEMENTS**

ACM - ICPC 2018

Competitive Programming Contest

Achieved a rank of 167 in The 2018 ICPC (International Collegiate Programming Contest) Asia Amritapuri Double site Regional Contest)

## Flipkart GRiD – Te[a]ch The Machines

2019